Preliminary Inventory of the Georg Nicolaus Knauer Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Georg Nicolaus Knauer papers,
1953-2001
83009
Knauer, Georg Nicolaus
24 manuscript boxes (10 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, notes, reports, press releases, newsletters, bulletins, and printed matter, relating to higher education and student radicalism in West Germany, especially at the Freie Universität Berlin, and to the organization and activities of the Notgemeinschaft für eine freie Universität and the Bund Freiheit der Wissenschaft.
Administrative Information
Access
Boxes 13-21 and 24 closed until 2021 March 5.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
German classical philologist; professor, Freie Universität Berlin, 1954-1974.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, notes, reports, press releases, newsletters, bulletins, and printed matter, relating to higher education and student radicalism in West Germany, especially at the Freie Universität Berlin, and to the organization and activities of the Notgemeinschaft für eine freie Universität and the Bund Freiheit der Wissenschaft.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Freie Universität Berlin.; Notgemeinschaft für eine freie Universität (Berlin, Germany); Education.; Education--Germany (West); Radicalism--Germany (West); Universities and colleges--Germany (West); Germany.; Conservatism.; Bund Freiheit der Wissenschaft.
Container List
- Notgemeinschaft publications, #1-120. (Box 1)
  Includes press releases of the Notgemeinschaft, and slides of the Berlin Office
- Notgemeinschaft publications, #121-339. (Box 2)
  Includes press releases of the Notgemeinschaft
- Notgemeinschaft publications, 1975-1977 (incomplete). (Box 3)
  Includes material from after 1975 January 1 [Georg N. Knauer's move to Philadelphia]
- Notgemeinschaft publications (incomplete), 1974 November 1 - 1981 December 1, but including #151-249 (Box 4)
- Notgemeinschaft publications, #1-149 [press releases not included] (Box 5)
- Notgemeinschaft publications, 1977-1980. (Box 6)
  Also material relating to Eberhard Lämmert, 1976; Hanns-Martin Schleyer, 1977; Georg Picht, Helmut Becker; and various other material, such as clippings, 1979
- Press clippings (Box 7)
- Material relating to Berlin, 1974; Bremen; Bund Freiheit der Wissenschaft (Box 8)
- Various publications, off prints, clippings, etc., relating to Alexander Schwan, Wilhelm Hennis, René Ahlberg, Ernst Nolte, Ernst Fraenkel, Richard Loewenthal (Box 9-12)
- CLOSED (Box 13-21)
- Notgemeinschaft publications, ca. 1972-1976 and 1986-1989 (incomplete, in disorder). (Box 22)
  Includes duplicates
- Notgemeinschaft publications (duplicates); material relating to the Bund Freiheit der Wissenschaft; the ICUE (International Council on the University Emergency); the "Hochschule in der Demokratie," 1964?; the "Kritische Universität (Berlin); Georg N. Knauer (Minerva); "Gutachten Borinski-Knauer" (Box 23)
- CLOSED (Box 24)